A Guide to the Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865
Library of Virginia
- 1828-039-SC: Admr. of John Draper vs Exrs. of Mitchell Clay, Etc.
  Contract Suit: John Draper complains that he is owed the value of the Rachel Findley, an enslaved woman, and several of her children out of the property of Mitchell Clay, dec'd. John Draper asserts that he and Mitchell Clay engaged in a transaction where Draper gave Clay a tract of Land in Giles County in exchange for Rachel and Jude, her child, although Clay knew at the time that Rachel was entitled to her freedom as a result of a general court ruling decreeing Rachel the descendant of illegally enslaved "Indian woman". In 1820 Rachel successfully sued for her freedom and subsequently so did some of her children and other decedents while being enslaved by the Draper family.
- 1830-029- SC: Peter Holley vs Admr. Of Joseph Baker, Etc.
  Contract Suit: Concerns contested tract of land in Wythe County which involved Joseph Baker, deceased. While the cause does not directly relate to the issue, the subject of Joseph Baker being killed by Bob and Sam, two men he enslaved, is referenced throughout the case.
- 1831-013-SC: David Pierce vs Thomas Jackson
  Contract Suit: Includes an extended discussion of the lives of enslaved people who were involved in lead mining, most prominently those who were killed or disabled in a mine collapse.
- 1831-023-SC: David Henning vs Daniel Wohlford, Etc.
  Debt Suit: Discusses a postmaster for the US Post Office who had been accused of stealing bank notes from a letter and altering the serial numbers. The postmaster subsequently accused an enslaved man of being the actual perpetrator of the theft and forgery.
- 1833-008-SC: Jonathan Ozbourne, Etc. vs Admr. of Stephen Ozbourne, Etc.
  Estate Suit: James Fullen, a white man, was accused of taking advantage of Stephen Ozbourne's alcoholism and poor mental health to convince Ozbourne to change his will. These changes included freeing an enslaved woman, Barbara, and the two children that Fullen had fathered with her. Includes documentation of Barbara's eventual freedom suit as well as a description of her experiences as an enslaved woman who was married to a free Black man, Austin Day.
- 1833-012-SC: P. J. Branch and wife vs Francis Preston
  Contract Suit: Francis Preston used P. J. Branch's wife's immigration status as evidence to invalidate her contractual rights to property purchased by her late, first husband. Preston argued that she was not an actual citizen because she had been born in Ireland, and thus had no dower rights related to her late husband's estate. She argued that her father's successful naturalization also applied to her. Includes naturalization records.
- 1833-033-SC: Alexander Thompson vs William H. Dulaney
  Contract Suit: Concerns a dispute over the validity of an exchange of enslaved people that was made while one party was intoxicated. Includes detailed descriptions of the lives, health, and occupations of these enslaved people, including enslaved children.
- 1833-041-SC: George Creger vs Adam Miller
  Debt Suit: Concerns the proceedings of a judicial slander case. This suit and the original slander case and center around an ongoing dispute over whether Adam Miller's father had died from an overdose of laudanum, or if he had died because of a beating that George Creger had given him the day before his death.
- 1834-009: John Davis vs William Houndshell
  Contract Suit: Centers around an enslaved woman suffering from a disease called "the white swelling"-likely what is known today as tuberculosis of the bones and joints. The suit discusses both the progression of her disease and the failure of her enslavers to provide adequate treatment throughout her illness.
- 1838-016: Exr. of Jane Robinson, Etc. vs Mitchell Robinson, Etc.
  Estate Suit: A group of enslaved people were accused of using their enslaver's dementia as a way to convince her to create a will that granted them their freedom.
- 1838-032-SC: Adam Waterford (Free) vs James Orr, Etc.
  Contract Suit: Adam Waterford was a free Black man who purchased a tract of Kentucky property from his former enslaver's family after he purchased his freedom. Waterford asserted that the land was smaller and less valuable than he had been promised, and that there were disputes within the family about the sale.
- 1840-015-SC: John Sanders and wife, Etc. vs John Jackson, Etc.
  Estate Suit: Dispute between family members over the property rights to a lead mine. Part of the family argued that the rest of the family didn't legally count as heirs, because they had immigrated from England and hadn't become naturalized citizens before the testator died. Includes naturalization records.
- 1845-024: James Hector vs Leonard Straw, Etc.
  Contract Suit: Concerns a dispute surrounding the property of Lewis Eisenmenger, a man who was involved in a land scheme to settle Saxon immigrants in western Virginia. Over one million acres of land in both Virginia and Kentucky were allegedly involved in this scheme over the course of Eisenmenger's lifetime, including over 22,000 acres in Tazewell and Russell Counties. The plaintiff James Hector claimed that he had agreed to help Eisenmenger survey the 22,000 acres in exchange for a portion of the proceeds from selling the property, only for Eisenmenger to sell the land for far lower than the market value.
- 1847-003-SC: David Pierce, Etc. vs James White, Etc.
  Business Suit: Regards the dissolution of a lead mining company, but much of the discussion centers on the experiences of workers employed by the business. This includes a discussion of the worker's efforts to negotiate for better wages, as well as descriptions of the food and clothing provided to them by the company. Additionally, one of the parties accused the other of paying the workers with devalued lead in place of the monetary wages that they had been promised. This suit also touches on the conditions experienced by enslaved workers hired out to the lead mine.
- 1847-016: Exr. Of Robert Porter Sr. vs Children of Andrew Porter, Etc.
  Estate Suit: Centers on an enslaved woman, Malvina, and her two young children, Mercury and Margaret, who were enslaved by the estate and heirs of Robert Porter. The two children lived with Malvina at the home of Robert's son Andrew until they were around eight years old, at which point Mercury and Margaret were considered old enough to be "hired out" and were separated from their mother. Because Malvina suffered from several health issues, Andrew's children argued that her labor had not been adequate compensation for the cost of raising her two young children. Depositions include discussions of the lives and care of Mercury and Margaret compared to the "usual" early lives of enslaved children.
- 1849-025: Robert Raper, Etc. vs Alexander Pierce
  Other: The plaintiffs accused Alexander Pierce of creating a safety hazard by conducting his lead mining business too close to a boarding house they had built for their workers. Pierce accused them of creating an unnecessary controversy to hurt his business, since he was one of their competitors. He claimed that there were no negative health risks associated with lead exposure, and that the point was irrelevant anyway because the boarding house was only a temporary structure that housed enslaved workers hired out to the plaintiffs. Testimony in this case included extensive debate over the existence of "lead colic," a chronic lead workers disease, and specifically whether enslaved former residents of the boarding house were suffering from it. Testimony also goes into detailed descriptions of the environmental effects of the lead mine, including poisonous water and smoke in the area and the frequent deaths of nearby plants and animals.
- 1854-027: William E. Sprinkle vs Stephen G. Wall etc.
  Contract Suit: Stephen Wall allegedly created a false deed of trust after he discovered that he had purchased an enslaved man who had been kidnapped and sold illegally. Wall was concerned that the possible legal action that this could cause would draw the attention of his creditors and used the deed to assuage their concerns. Deponents in the suit claimed that Wall was especially concerned about legal attention because he had previously been involved in a scheme to kidnap a different enslaved man and illegally sell him in North Carolina.
- 1858-022: John D. Miller vs Margaret J. Miller
  Divorce Suit: John D. Miller accused his wife Margaret of not only having multiple affairs and engaging in sex work, but also moving to Tennessee to escape prosecution for attempting to murder another woman who was involved with one of her lovers. Included as evidence were several examples of Margaret's correspondence that discuss her affairs, including messages written to a partner regarding the best times and places for them to meet.
- 1860-006: Julia A. Thomas vs James D. Thomas
  Divorce Suit: Julia A. Thomas accused her husband James D. Thomas of extensive physical and emotional abuse throughout their marriage. The abuse culminated in John kidnapping their young child to force Julia to sign over the rights to dower land, leading Julia's father and brother-in-law to smuggle money to her to help her run away from their home. John retaliated by attempting to sue his father-in-law and extended family for convincing and aiding his wife to escape. Notable matters covered in this suit include discussions of contemporaneous birth control methods and religious attitudes towards them, depositions by John's former students at an all-girls school discussing their experiences as students and boarders, and accusations by John that his in-laws were connected to "women of ill-repute" and unwed mothers.
- 1860-032: Charlotte Fulford vs Francis Fulford
  Divorce Suit: Charlotte Fulford was seeking a divorce from her husband after he abandoned her and their child while they were living in Iowa in order to move to California to participate in the gold rush. Charlotte was forced to sell most of the family's property to fund their return to Virginia, and then support herself and her child alone by working as a schoolteacher.